בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף, daf, happy חנוכה, Chanukah, second day.
Today's דף, daf, today is two days to be חנוכה. Chanukah. Okay,
today's דף daf is דף טז עמוד א. Daf Tet Zayin Vav
Amud Aleph. That's sixteen, very top of the page. As you know,
I was a little bit sick and out of it yesterday, so
I want to just mention a couple points that I did not
get a chance to mention yesterday.
So first of all, רש״י Rashi says the process that we're dealing
with now about when they walk around to sanctify the area, I
did not mention this, but there is an interesting debate of רש״י
Rashi and תוספות, Tosfos, do they walk around the inside of the
perimeter of the new space or the outside of the perimeter of
the new space? So and part of the challenge is because the
last thing we started to discuss yesterday is that of these two
breads of the תודה Todah that they would bring, one of them
would be burnt and one of them would be eaten. And the
גמרא Gemara seems to say that the relevant issue there is who's
going into the sanctified, at least גמרא Gemara initially thought, the first
one going into sanctified or unsanctified space when it was first entering
in. So רש״י Rashi says that they're both walking on the outside
of the perimeter. Okay, but the problem that תוספות Tosfos has with
that is if they're both on the outside of the perimeter and
what they're sanctifying, first of all, it's a little bizarre, they're walking
on the outside and they're sanctifying what's in there, but he also
says that then both of those breads should be invalid because even
after you're done with the procession, they're on the outside, they're not
in the sanctified space. So תוספות Tosfos therefore says they're both walking
on the inside. Okay, and then the only question, and then it
explains why the גמרא Gemara thinks that if they're going single file,
that the first one, because the first one is sanctifying, because if
the old wall was here
and the new wall is here and then this starts as unsanctified
space, then if you imagine, if you start let's say you come,
let's say you start walking in like this and you go like
that, right, so then the first one clears the mine as I
said,
the first one is constantly sanctifying the space
and becoming invalid in the process while the second one is following
it. So that works. The גמרא Gemara rejects that because the גמרא
Gemara says they have to work together. But at least that's what
תוספות Tosfos says and makes a lot of sense that they're walking
against the wall on the inside of the new space, not on
the inside of the perimeter, not the outside. Okay, so that's how
תוספות Tosfos explains it. תוספות's Tosfos only problem is that there's actually
a הלכה, halacha, here's an interesting הלכה, halacha, is the thickness of
the wall also have the sanctity of the space on the inside?
Like if somebody is in a gate inside of the wall? So
the הלכה halacha basically is that it does and תוספות Tosfos sort
of says well it's a little hard to understand since they're only
walking on the inside of the perimeter how they sanctify the thickness
of the wall, but he sort of says you got no choice
so you do what you do. Okay, so anyway that I thought
was an interesting and important debate that I didn't...
But you could have just had one on the inside, one on
the very outside, I mean the space between...
Yeah, that could have also explained why one is burnt and one
isn't burnt, that's a good point, but I don't know what to
say about that, that is a good point.
Yeah, since they build that wall after they sanctify...
No,
the whole point was that you sanctify the space, the wall defined
the outer perimeter and then you sanctify the space, and that was
the whole גמרא's Gemara discussion why you can't do it with the
bread of on
שבועות, Shavuos, because you'd have to finish the building and sanctify it
on the day of the building and therefore you can't even do
one stone afterwards because you can't build at night, right, so that
was the whole sort of discussion.
גמרא Gemara says shouldn't the פסוק pasuk have said לחמי תודה Lachmei
Todah or something? I mean because they said...
Yeah, what could I tell you Michael, it's a דרשה. drasha. Okay,
alright, so fine, so now let's take a look, let's take a
look.
One minute,
let me see if there was another תוספות Tosfos I wanted to
mention.
Yeah, תוספות's Tosfos other question is so we've explained that you sanctify
ירושלים Yerushalayim by using the breads of a תודה, Todah, which can
only be eaten up to the, can only be in the walls
of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, not outside. You sanctify the עזרה Azarah
by the remnant of a מנחה, Mincha, which is similar, it's flour
and water although it's מצה matzah not חמץ, chametz, because a מנחה
Mincha can only be eaten in the עזרה. Azarah. תוספות Tosfos says
let's say you wanted to expand or initially sanctify, like the first
time they went in, הר הבית, Har HaBayis, which has a status
of מחנה לויה, Machaneh Leviyah, so that would be the עזרת נשים,
Ezras Nashim, it would be the whole הר הבית. Har HaBayis. So
you could say well maybe you can't go beyond הר הבית, Har
HaBayis, it's only the mountain, but not necessarily, I mean what are
the parameters? Maybe the parameters may be the space that's considered מחנה
לויה, Machaneh Leviyah, the Levite camp, which the most relevant is like
what טמא tamei person can go in or not, okay, and that's
not a relevant for קרבנות, korbanos, it's only a relevance for a
certain level of טומאה tumah can go into that space, okay, and
a certain level cannot go into that space. So תוספות Tosfos says
it's really not clear how you would sanctify like הר הבית. Har
HaBayis. And if you take a look at this short תוספות Tosfos
on the bottom of
the page.
I'm sorry, not that one, no, I'm sorry, yeah, bottom of ט"ו
עמוד א', tes vav amud aleph, היוצא ממנו נפסל, hayotzei mimenu nifsal,
he says, ואם תאמר הר הבית היכי קדיש שאין דבר נאכל בה
שיוצא ממנו נפסל. ve'im tomar Har HaBayis heichi kadish she'ein davar ne'echal
bah sheyotzei mimenu nifsal. הר הבית's Har HaBayis line is not defined
by different קרבנות, korbanos, so you don't have an idea of use
a קרבן korban that can only go up to that limit. הר
הבית Har HaBayis is basically the space of, you know, that a
certain type of טמא tamei person can't go in. So he says,
so תוספות Tosafos says, and he says, ויש לומר היכא דלא אפשר
לא אפשר. ve'yesh lomar heicha delo efshar lo efshar. Well, if you
can't use the bread, you don't use the bread. Presumably you do
the procession, you know, a similar type of a procession, but you
don't have the idea. But the funny thing is that this is
very highly symbolic. You know, using the bread is saying, "This is
the outer limit for this thing." But תוספות Tosafos says, for at
least הר הבית, Har HaBayis, you would not be able to do
that. And as I said, I think an interesting parallel is, and
this is not based on the גמרא Gemara at all, the idea
that candle lighting is the act that separates weekday from שבת. Shabbos.
You know, the last thing you do in a weekday is a
מלאכה, melacha, okay, but in a way, you know, so that developed
after the גמרא, Gemara, but it's a similar type of an idea.
You do this thing that sort of is signifying the boundary. After
this, this thing can't be done. Okay, so let's continue now, okay,
with,
what do you call it?
What? הבדלה Havdalah also.
Yeah, הבדלה Havdalah is at the other side. That's a good point.
The lighting of the candles, הבדלה Havdalah is the other side of
that. That's absolutely correct. Okay, so let's take a look now top
of ט"ז עמוד א'. tes zayin amud aleph. כל שלא נעשה בכל
אלו. kol shelo na'asah bechol elu. Any one, anything that was not
done with all of these components is not a valid sanctification. איתמר,
itmar, it was taught. רב הונא Rav Huna אמר, amar, בכל אלו
תנן, bechol elu tnan, only if you used all of these components:
כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, מלך, Melech, נביא, Navi, you know, 71, בית
דין Beis Din of 71, the whole shebang, okay, תנן. tnan. רב
נחמן Rav Nachman אמר, amar, באחת מכל אלו תנן, be'achas mikol elu
tnan,
any one of these components. Exactly. Okay, תנן. tnan.
Now רב הונא Rav Huna אמר, amar, בכל אלו תנן, bechol elu
tnan, now what's this based on? So רב הונא Rav Huna says
it has to have all of them. What it's based on is
the problem that the whole basis for this procession that we learn
from נחמיה, Nechemya, okay, at the time of נחמיה, Nechemya, there was
no king yet. I mean, you could say maybe, you know, there
was heads of the nation, but there were certainly no אורים ותומים.
Urim V'Tummim. And it said a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol with אורים
ותומים. Urim V'Tummim. Okay, so you didn't have all these components at
the time of נחמיה. Nechemya. So how, so you know, what's going
on there? So if you say, if you say בכל אלו
תנן, bechol elu tnan, you needed all of them, and therefore, and
therefore they didn't do it at the time of נחמיה Nechemya properly.
קסבר קדושה ראשונה קידשה לשעתה וקידשה לעתיד לבוא. kasavar kedusha rishona kidsha
l'sha'ata v'kidsha l'asid lavo. The original
sanctification of ירושלים Yerushalayim and the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash was for
its time, the first one, at the time of דוד, David, I
guess, would be for its time and for all future times. So
therefore, you did not need to re-sanctify it. Now, here's the point.
Because in the time of נחמיה, Nechemya, they weren't expanding the boundaries.
They were doing a sanctification of the basic boundaries. They came in,
everything was destroyed, they were sanctifying the space.
So saying you didn't need to sanctify the space in the time
of נחמיה Nechemya because it was already sanctified from the time of
דוד, David, okay, and שלמה, Shlomo, whenever exactly you say that moment
was. So therefore he says, what they did in נחמיה Nechemya was,
you're right, they didn't have all the components, but they didn't need
to do it.
ועזרא זכר בעלמא הוא דעבד, ve'Ezra zeicher b'alma hu d'avid, and that
which was done there was just a זכר, zeicher, was just a,
you know, a little memorial, a way of evoking what had been
done in the past, you know, obviously was symbolically significant. We're coming
back to a destroyed temple, we're going to rebuild it, we want
to show that we're re-designating the space as sanctified ground, you know,
sort of like the חנוכת הבית Chanukas HaBayis we're talking about חנוכה,
Chanukah, right? You know, it might be that halachically it didn't need
a dedication, but you know, nationally, communally, symbolically, it needed a new
dedication, but it did not really have any halachic significance. Now, once
that's true, by the way, what that means is, is that ever
since the חורבן churban of the first בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, okay,
we don't need to re-sanctify, but it also means we can't extend
the boundaries. The whole point of the משנה Mishnah that you could
grow the boundaries of ירושלים Yerushalayim and of whatever, right, would have
been limited to the time of the first בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
according to this, because we don't have all the components anymore.
Does it require אורים ותומים Urim V'Tummim just to have like the
official כהן גדול Kohen Gadol in all his regalia, or like you
actually need to like sort of ask God?
Oh, that's a good question. Right, you know, whether so, תוספות Tosafos
actually says at one place that the אורים ותומים Urim V'Tummim means
you have to be שואל באורים ותומים. shoel b'Urim V'Tummim. So it's
an excellent question. I don't know what תוספות Tosafos assumes there, but
in a certain discussion, תוספות Tosafos says like maybe, you know, you
need like divine approval which is sought through the אורים ותומים. Urim
V'Tummim. That's not explicit, but that's, you know, that's an excellent point.
Okay, so he says this, this was not really, this was not
halachically significant. רב נחמן Rav Nachman אמר, amar, באחת מכל אלו תנן.
be'achas mikol elu tnan. No, you can use any one of them,
and any one of the
components. קסבר קדושה ראשונה קידשה לשעתה ולא קידשה לעתיד לבוא. kasavar kedusha
rishona kidsha l'sha'ata v'lo kidsha l'asid lavo. The sanctity of the time
of דוד David and שלמה Shlomo did not last for all time;
it was lost. At the time of the destruction of the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash and they had to resanctify it. ועזרא קידש לשעתה
V'Ezra kidesh l'shaata and עזרא Ezra did resanctify. According to him, therefore,
this ability exists, you know, even in the time of the second
בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, who knows? Maybe does it exist even today?
I mean, do we have any one of those? Do we have
a מלך? Melech? I mean, I guess, you know, so it depends
I guess how you define the Prime Minister or the king or
the president. Okay, but in theory any one of those therefore they
were able to do it in עזרא Ezra and certainly throughout the
time of the second בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash they could have expanded
the boundaries of the city and so on. Okay, אף על גב
דלא הוו אורים ותומים, af al gav d'lo havu urim v'tumim, even
though there was no
אורים ותומים. urim v'tumim. Okay, איתי רבא לרב נחמן. aisei Rava l'Rav
Nachman. So רבא Rava challenged רב נחמן Rav Nachman because רב נחמן
Rav Nachman said that it was that you can use any one
of the components. Okay, you don't need all of that. And therefore,
that's based on the idea that קדושה ראשונה kidusha rishona is לא
קידשה לעתיד לבוא lo kidesha l'atid lavo that it needed to be
resanctified and it was resanctified.
So he asked רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, כולהו אנוסיס בכל אלו תנן.
Koshla anuseis bechol eilu tnan. It says all of them. So רב
נחמן Rav Nachman says back, באחת מכל אלו. Bachas mikol eilu. תני
באחת מכל אלו. Tani bachas mikol eilu. Alright, stick in a word
one of. Okay, it says all of them, stick the word one
of all of them, one of any, any of them. Okay, תוספות
Tosafos actually says it wasn't such a question, sometimes the phrase itself
actually means that, you know, you don't even have to really edit
the text. But anyway, okay, תא שמע, ta shma, come and hear.
Now we're going to get into this question of like what's קדושה
ראשונה kidusha rishona or not קדושה ראשונה. kidusha rishona. אבא שאול אומר,
Abba Shaul omer, אבא שאול Abba Shaul says: שני ביצאין, Shenei bitza'in,
two swamps, actually ties into the to this week's פרשה parsha because
if you look at רש"י, Rashi, ביצאין. bitza'in. No,
not that. Yeah, like 10 lines down the narrow lines, ביצאין, bitza'in,
רש"י Rashi says מרסקה בלעז. mariska belaz. Well, that's very helpful. But
you look at the sides and the side says והוא ויז בלשון
אשכנז ve'hu vis belashon Ashkenaz also not helpful.
Okay, ותעמדנה באחו, vata'amodna ba'achu, which is this week's פרשה, parsha, another
sign of צער מסיני, tzar missinai, not only this falls out on
חנוכה Chanukah for פרשת מקץ, parshas Mikeitz, פירוש רש"י, peirush Rashi, מרסקה
בלעז. mariska belaz. So now we know that אחו ach that's a
swamp. By going from the גמרא Gemara to רש"י's Rashi old French
word back to the פסוק pasuk in the חומש, Chumash, now we
know what it means. That's like the German Jews who learned German
because of, you know, what's his name's translation,
Mendelssohn's translation. He translated
the תורה Torah into German and it didn't help people understand the
Hebrew they couldn't understand, it helped them understand their German they couldn't
understand. Anyway, it's a סימן. siman.
What?
We had that in the גמרא, Gemara, ומאי ביצאין?
v'mai bitza'in? Yeah, oh that's true too. There you go. Okay, so
like dirty ponds or swamps. Okay. אבא שאול אומר: Abba Shaul omer:
שני ביצאין היו בהר המשחה. Shenei bitza'in hayu b'Har HaMishcha. There was
in the Mount Olives. תחתונה ועליונה, Tachtona v'elyona, the lower one and
then the one higher up on the slope. תחתונה נתקדשה בכל אלו
Tachtona niskadsha b'chol eilu and they expanded the boundaries of
ירושלים Yerushalayim to include the Mount Olives, okay, but so but there
was two boundary lines. One with an old wall that incorporated the
lower swamp and one with a newer wall that incorporated the swamp
that was higher up on the slope. You got the idea? Okay,
so here it was. They wanted to get Hebrew University and Mount
Scopus into the boundaries of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. תחתונה ועליונה. Tachtona v'elyona. תחתונה
נתקדשה
בכל אלו. Tachtona niskadsha b'chol eilu. Okay, no, that's הר צופים, Har
Tzofim, this is הר המשחה. Har HaMishcha. Okay, sorry.
So anyway, so the bottom one, תחתונה נתקדשה בכל אלו. Tachtona niskadsha
b'chol eilu. So the bottom one was sanctified with all of these
things, meaning from the time of the first בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
So presumably that was included in the real קדושה kidusha of ירושלים.
Yerushalayim. עליונה לא נתקדשה בכל אלו, Elyona lo niskadsha b'chol eilu, the
top one was not sanctified with all of these, אלא בעולי גולה,
ella b'olei golah, but it was when they came up in the
time from the exile in the time of עזרא. Ezra. So the
first one had the sanctity from the first בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash,
the further expansion of boundaries was only from the time of עזרא.
Ezra. And presumably what that means is the first one has the
real sanctity of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, the second one does not. שלא במלך,
Shelo b'melech, ah, you see not only that it didn't have an
אורים ותומים, urim v'tumim, it also didn't have a king, even though
they had a political leader. שלא במלך ושלא באורים ותומים. Shelo b'melech
v'shelo b'urim v'tumim. And what's the result of this? תחתונה שהייתה קדושתה
גמורה, Tachtona shehayesa kedushasa gemura, so he's quite explicit. The bottom one,
the sanctity was complete. עמי הארץ נכנסים לשם, Amei ha'aretz nichnasim l'sham,
so the עמי הארץ amei ha'aretz would go there and אוכלים שם
קדשים קלים, v'ochlim sham kodashim kalim, they would eat sacrifices, אבל לא
מעשר שני. aval lo ma'aser sheni. Now, רש"י Rashi it's funny, רש"י
Rashi sort of changes the גרסא girsa but it's not exactly clear.
I think what רש"י Rashi is saying, I have to look at
like somebody who has a more a newer version of the גמרא
Gemara here. But anyway, I think רש"י's Rashi גרסא girsa was אוכלים
שם קדשים קדשים וקדשים קלים ומעשר שני. ochlim sham kodashim kodashim u'kodashim
kalim u'ma'aser sheni.
I don't know, what do they say in your English? Do they
translate it not מעשר שני ma'aser sheni or do they say and
מעשר שני? ma'aser sheni?
It says oh would eat קדשים קלים kodashim kalim there and מעשר
שני.
ma'aser sheni. Right. That's how רש"י Rashi seems to be wanting to
change the גרסא, girsa, although there's a גרסא girsa problem in רש"י
Rashi himself. Okay, so anyway, רש"י's Rashi read of this is that
the עמי הארץ amei ha'aretz would eat there both קדשים קלים kodashim
kalim and מעשר שני. ma'aser sheni.
But why would you have a גרסא girsa of not מעשר שני?
ma'aser sheni?
I don't know why, the question is what is the text you
have to work with and then you have to explain it backwards.
No that's what I'm saying. I don't know, well that's why רש"י
Rashi changes the גרסא. girsa. קדשי קלים ומעשר שני kodshei kalim u'ma'aser
sheni they would eat everything because why not, it had full sanctity.
והחברים אוכלין שם קדשי קלים ומעשר שני ve'hachaveirim ochlin sham kodshei kalim
u'ma'aser sheni and also the חברים chaveirim the people that were more
punctilious about תרומות ומעשרות trumos u'ma'aseros and טהרה tahara would eat there
also both things. Why not? Full sanctity. העליונה Ha'elyonah however the upper
space שלא היתה קדושתה גמורה shelo hayta kedushata gemurah it was not
fully sanctified, עם הארץ היו נכנסין שם ואוכלין שם קדשי קלים אבל
לא מעשר שני am ha'aretz hayu nichnasin sham v'ochlin sham kodshei kalim
aval lo ma'aser sheni they wouldn't eat מעשר שני ma'aser sheni there.
והחברים אין אוכלין שם לא קדשי קלים ולא מעשר שני ve'hachaveirim ein
ochlin sham lo kodshei kalim v'lo ma'aser sheni and they wouldn't eat
either because it's not really sanctified. So the עם הארץ am ha'aretz
who didn't know better they would eat there but the חברים chaveirim
who knew better wouldn't eat there. Now the question of course is
if the
עם הארץ am ha'aretz really don't know better why did they distinguish
when it comes to the מעשר שני? ma'aser sheni? So רש״י Rashi
says and this is interesting because normally you think that the עם
הארץ am ha'aretz are sort of lax in areas of תרומות
ומעשרות trumos u'ma'aseros but רש״י Rashi says maybe they also know of
the דרשה. drasha. There's a דרשה, drasha, this is what רש״י Rashi
says, עשר תעשר aser te'aser you shall surely take your tithe, עשר
בשביל שתתעשר aser bishvil she'tis-asher give your tithe so that you will
become rich. And somehow maybe they felt that the מעשר ma'aser is
very special we want to go into the ancient city of ירושלים
Yerushalayim into the within the inner walls whereas קרבנות korbanos קרבנות korbanos
it's of course exactly ironic any normal person would assume קרבנות korbanos
are
weightier.
They're מפריש תרומה mafrish trumah which is an עשה aseh מעשר ma'aser
I know the whole thing is bizarre. I can't explain it. But
what's relevant for us you can work on that for your homework
assignment but what's relevant for us is clearly that the expansion of
the second בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash does not have full
sanctity. And the חברים chaveirim knew that and it wasn't considered ירושלים.
Yerushalayim.
By the way I'm going to pause for a second and say
that if you remember a while ago we actually learned this whole
thing about a tree that was part in ירושלים Yerushalayim out of
ירושלים Yerushalayim עיר מקלט
ir
miklat but also the עיר מקלט ir miklat but also discussed eating
מעשר שני ma'aser sheni and there's two ways of thinking about the
קדושה kedusha of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. One way of thinking about the קדושה
kedusha of ירושלים Yerushalayim is that it's the extended courtyard of the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash it's an extension because you eat קרבנות korbanos
in all of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. But the other way of thinking about
it is that it's just a heightened sanctity of ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael or if you would it's the capital city if you want
to say it that way to relate to contemporary concepts but not
to become too
political. And therefore the difference is that that idea that you eat
מעשר שני לפני ה׳ ma'aser sheni lifnei Hashem you don't bring מעשר
שני ma'aser sheni to the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. You eat מעשר
שני לפני ה׳. ma'aser sheni lifnei Hashem. So therefore maybe you could
have a לפני ה׳ lifnei Hashem aspect which is not exactly defined
in the same way the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash parameters are. It's
really interesting to think about this idea. Could you say that the
sanctity that they did the גמרא Gemara isn't saying this because it's
making it the עם הארץ am ha'aretz so here I am defending
the
עם הארץ. am ha'aretz. But it's a great hypothetical theoretical model that
the sanctity that they did in the second בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
because it didn't have all the components it was not meaningful in
terms of extending the sanctity that's
מקדש mikdash related. The sanctity that's related to the בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash which is because that's what this is it's all about using
the breads and the sacrifices and so on. So therefore for קרבנות
korbanos purpose it was only the inner zone
exactly opposite of what the עם הארץ am ha'aretz were saying. But
it's a good idea. You could say that for קרבנות korbanos purpose
it's only the inner zone because this is a sanctity that's בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash related but maybe for other purposes maybe it would
be even what they did in the second בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
time. Anyway I just want to point that out that thinking about
the difference of מעשר שני ma'aser sheni and קרבנות korbanos is interesting
could you theoretically divide two different statuses of ירושלים Yerushalayim and think
about them having different parameters for those two things. But for us
the point is that it makes it clear that the second sanctity
that the first sanctity is the one that counted and not the
second
one. נימא לא קידשוה nima lo kidshuha now why did they not
why was the second extension not fully sanctified? שאין מוסיפין על העיר
ועל העזרות אלא במלך ונביא ואורים ותומים she'ein mosifin al ha'ir ve'al
ha'azarot ela be'melech ve'navi v'urim v'tumim you need all these components. If
you want to extend the boundaries you need a king and a
prophet and אורים ותומים urim v'tumim ובסנהדרין של שבעים ואחד ובשתי תודות
u'be'sanhedrin shel shiv'im ve'echad u'bishtei todot and two of these peace offerings
ובשיר u'v'shir and with song. ולמה קידשוה v'lama kidshuha so if you
couldn't extend it why did they bother sanctifying
it? If it didn't work why did they do this in the
time of עזרא ונחמיה? Ezra v'Nehemiah? So the גמרא Gemara says ולמה
קידשוה lama kidshuha what do you mean why they sanctified it הא
אמרת לא קידשוה ha amart lo kidshuha what do you mean why
they sanctified it you just got through saying they didn't sanctify it.
But the obvious point is why did they make it look like
they sanctified it? Why did they go through with this ritual? אלא
למה הכניסוה ela lama hichnisuha why did they incorporate
why did they do this ritual that even though it did not
have the power to really extend the boundaries of ירושלים Yerushalayim but
it symbolically was doing that and it symbolically was incorporating this extra
space into ירושלים Yerushalayim so why did they bother doing it if
it wasn't going to actually sanctify it as a technical הלכה? halakha?
halakhic thing. So the גמרא Gemara says מפני שטורפה של ירושלים היתה,
mipnei she-turpa shel Yerushalayim hayta, because it was the nakedness of ירושלים,
Yerushalayim, meaning it was a vulnerable area, ונוח היא ליכבש משם, v'noach
hi lekavesh misham, and it would be easy to attack ירושלים Yerushalayim
from that direction, and therefore they wanted from the people's perspective people
to see this as actually part of ירושלים Yerushalayim and presumably they
built, the way רש"י Rashi explains it, they built up the wall
to that outer limit. So you want to do this whole ritual
and build the wall and even if technically speaking it doesn't have
the sanctity, okay, that this is part of, you know, getting people
to own this in a deep emotional way and to formally, you
know, incorporate this into ירושלים. Yerushalayim. All right, so anyway that's a
great little historical explanation, but it's clear that it's only the sanctity
from the time of the first בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So the
גמרא Gemara says תנאי היא. tanna'i hi. You're right, it's a debate
of תנאים, tannaim, said would say רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. I who
say that they could that they resanctified it, I'm, you know, I'm
siding like a different תנא tanna that holds that it's the second
sanctity that they that counts and that you don't need all the
components. Now, where do we have that debate that other side that
says you can that they sanctified it in the time of Ezra,
Nehemiah? דתניא, detanya, we taught in a ברייתא, braisa, אמר רבי אלעזר,
Amar Rabbi Elazar, שמעתי כשהיו בונים בהיכל, shamati k'shehayu bonim baheichal, I
heard that when they were building in the second בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash and they were building in the היכל, heichal, right, this is
the, this is the היכל, heichal, okay, that when they were building
in the היכל, heichal,
עשו קלעים להיכל וקלעים לעזרות. asu kla'im laheichal v'kla'im la'azaros. So what
they would do is you would build a wall, but, you know,
they would they would sort of they would sort of put up
some curtains here, okay, hang up a little and then they would
work on building up this wall. So they wouldn't be like as
they're building looking into the space that's going to become sanctified space.
You know, I mean sure, it's true that before they started building
the whole space was desolate. But if you're trying to rebuild and
resanctify the space, you have to start doing things that shows your,
you know, your sensitivity to this holy space. So since of course
normally only כהנים kohanim could go in here, you don't want as
you're building to be like, you know, looking at it that will
have a desacralizing type of emotional effect. So they put up curtains
around the space and they built the wall on the outside of
the curtains. Okay, עשו קלעים להיכל וקלעים לעזרות. asu kla'im laheichal v'kla'im
la'azaros. And similarly when they were building up the עזרות azaros here,
right, the עזרת כהנים ezras kohanim and עזרת ישראל, ezras Yisrael, excuse
me, עזרת נשים ezras nashim as well although this halakhically is the
technical עזרה, azarah, okay, אלא שבהיכל בונים מבחוץ, ella shebaheichal bonim mibachutz,
but what I said when they built the היכל heichal they built
it on the outside of the curtain, ועזרות בונים מבפנים, v'azaros bonim
mibifnim, and when they built the עזרה, azarah, since this space wasn't
as sanctified, the builders were behind like, you know, on the inside
of the curtain. Okay, so in that case the קלעים kla'im were
not so much that they shouldn't see but more to like demarcate
the space, or maybe that's, you know, outside people who are just
walking by shouldn't be gawking in and seeing. Okay, אמר רבי יהושע,
Amar Rabbi Yehoshua, so that's what רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar said. Said
רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, שמעתי שמקריבים אף על פי שאין בית, shamati
shemakrivim af al pi she'ein bayis, אוכלים קדשי קדשים אף על פי
שאין קלעים. ochlim kodshei kodashim af al pi she'ein kla'im. I heard
that you can bring קרבנות korbanos even without a בית המקדש, Beis
HaMikdash,
which is the whole basis on which people want to bring a
קרבן פסח korban pesach nowadays, and you could eat קדשי קדשים kodshei
kodashim even though there were not these curtains, because these curtains, okay,
define the עזרה, azarah, the עזרה azarah was the space that you
eat קדשי קדשים. kodshei kodashim. So he says you could eat the
קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim even without the קלעים. kla'im. Okay, אוכלים קדשי
קדשים
אף על פי שאין קלעים, ochlim kodshei kodashim af al pi she'ein
kla'im, קדשים קלים ומעשר שני אף על פי שאין חומה, kodashim kalim
u'ma'aser sheni af al pi she'ein chomah, and you could eat the
stuff that's eaten in ירושלים Yerushalayim without the wall. Now why? How
could you do that? You know, presumably don't we need the physical
structure to define the sanctity? Didn't the sanctity go away when the
structure was destroyed? And he says no, the structure is just something
physical, the sanctity never leaves. מפני שקדושה ראשונה קידשה לשעתה וקידשה לעתיד
לבוא, mipnei she-kedusha rishona kidsha lish'ata v'kidsha l'asid lavo, because that original
sanctity lasts even after the destruction. And therefore because the sanctity's there,
now it's one thing to say the sanctity is there, you might
still say that to bring a קרבן, korban, you know, sanctity says
I don't know, can I go in when I'm טמא? tamei? Right?
You might still say that you need certain physical apparatuses in order
to bring a קרבן korban or whatever. Right, a מזבח. mizbeach. Well
you do need a מזבח, mizbeach, but you might think you need
a whole בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash to bring a קרבן, korban, right.
Sanctity and whether you can bring a קרבן korban are not necessarily,
just because there's sanctity doesn't mean it's sufficient, but he's saying it
is. Now I do want to say something also about the power
of this point, because this point emphasizes that the sanctity remains even
though the physical sort of, you know, building got destroyed. And רמב"ם
Rambam sort of explains this because רמב"ם Rambam says in this תוספות
Tosafos here actually discusses, here's a fascinating question. Does the question of
the original sanctity of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, if it lasts,
you know, after the חורבן, churban, is that the same question as
the sanctity of the land of Israel and did that last after
the exile? So תוספות Tosafos in a few places and רמב"ם Rambam
say that those are not theoretically linked. Now תוספות Tosafos in a
few places considers that they could go either way. You could say
that you have the sanctity of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash now
without the sanctity of the land of Israel. Okay, meaning what's, what's
the halakhic relevance of the sanctity of the land of Israel? The
most basic halakhic relevance of that?
The sanctity? Land of Israel? Whether there's in, you know,
of שמיטות?
Shmittos? Right, whether there's an obligation of תרומות Trumos and מעשרות Ma'asros
and שמיטה, Shmittah, all the agricultural. So in one place תוספות Tosafos
says, I mean תוספות Tosafos here and רמב״ם Rambam says that you
can have the sanctity of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash without the
sanctity of the land in terms of תרומות Trumos and מעשרות. Ma'asros.
In another place תוספות Tosafos suggests the flip. You can have the
sanctity of the land without the sanctity of the מקדש. Mikdash. And
to some degree you can understand both of those. Right? The sanctity
of the land, you know, the מקדש Mikdash you might say requires
the structure of the מקדש, Mikdash, right? And things that are connected
to the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, whereas the land is still the
land. Okay, but what's the explanation of this split? That which is
what רמב״ם Rambam rules as well. That the sanctity of the land
goes away, but the sanctity of the מקדש Mikdash remains. So רמב״ם
Rambam says because the sanctity of the מקדש, Mikdash, even if it
was inaugurated through the building of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, ultimately
it's defined as the place where השראת השכינה hashras hashkhina or God's
presence dwelt. And רמב״ם Rambam says once God's presence has dwelt in
a particular place, you know, it continues to dwell there. That place
continues to remain holy because of that sense of God's presence. So
the land of Israel is not the—and this gets into interesting questions—what's
the sort of metaphysical significance of the קדושה kedusha of ארץ ישראל?
Eretz Yisrael? But it's not about, רמב״ם Rambam says, God's presence. It's
really about the fact that it's under Jewish sovereignty, or it's where
Jews are living. Okay, you know, sovereignty is the first בית המקדש,
Beis Hamikdash, Jews are living is the second בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
Alright. So—
But there is...
I understand,
just
דאורייתא de'oraisa it's השראת השכינה. hashras hashkhina.
Okay, but yeah, I just wanted to point that out that the
emphasis here that רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua is making, that you can
build, bring קרבנות korbanos without a בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, and it's
קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim without a בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, what he's
saying is the physical structure is not significant, right? At least when
we're talking about the מקדש, Mikdash, and interesting to think if Israel's
the same or not, but when we're talking about the מקדש, Mikdash,
God's presence, right, and that sanctity is still there without the physical
structure. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says now, this is being brought
as to try to prove that there's a debate of תנאים Tannaim
whether it's the first sanctity or the second sanctity. Okay. Now we
clearly have the position here of רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua that the
first sanctity is what matters. Do you see in the original statement
of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that he says that you built these
קלעים, kelayim, an opposing position? So that's what the גמרא Gemara wants
to argue. Okay, it goes like this. Okay, so מאי לאו—so mai
lav says, 'לפי שלא'—מאי לאו מכלל דרבי אליעזר, mikh'lal d'Rabbi Eliezer,
so
רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says you can bring קרבנות korbanos without a
structure, so presumably רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer who's emphasizing that they put
up קלעים, kelayim, presumably he's saying you can't bring קרבנות korbanos without
a structure. You need a structure and you need to resanctify the
space, which would be saying that it's the second sanctity. מאי לאו
מכלל דרבי אליעזר סבר לא קדשה לעתיד לבוא? mai lav mikh'lal d'Rabbi
Eliezer savar lo kidsha l'asid lavo?
Shouldn't we infer from this that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer who's talking
about putting up the קלעים kelayim is saying that they didn't sanctify
it, that the sanctity did not remain from the first בית המקדש,
Beis Hamikdash, and you needed to resanctify it and you needed the
structure? So גמרא Gemara says, אמר ליה רבינא לרב אשי ממאי? amar
lei Ravina l'Rav Ashi mi'mai? Says who? דילמא דכולי עלמא קדושה ראשונה
קדשה לשעתה וקדשה לעתיד
לבוא. dilma d'kholei alma kedusha rishona kidsha l'sha'ata v'kidsha l'asid lavo. Maybe
everybody agrees that the first sanctity remained. מר מאי דשמיע ליה קאמר
ומר מאי דשמיע ליה קאמר. mar mai d'shmia lei ka'amar, u'mar mai
d'shmia lei ka'amar. They're not disagreeing, they're just each one is contributing
some of the tradition that they had. One said, 'I heard they
put up קלעים,' kelayim, and the other said, 'Yes, you're right, they
did put up קלעים,' kelayim, or, 'But you don't need the קלעים.'
kelayim. By saying they put up קלעים kelayim isn't a disagreeing position,
he's just contributing a historical fact. Okay. וכי תימא קלעים לרבי אליעזר
למה לי?
v'khi
teima
kelayim l'Rabbi Eliezer lama li? So if you don't need the קלעים
kelayim for the sanctity, the sanctity remains, why did you put up
the קלעים? kelayim? לצניעותא בעלמא, l'tzni'uta b'alma, like I was telling you,
for modesty reasons, so you shouldn't be like looking at this space
that's not appropriate to be seen and so on. Okay. So now
we still don't have anybody to back רב נחמן Rav Nachman who
says that you needed to sanctify it a second time and that
it's enough to have one of the components. So far all of
our Tannaic evidence is either vague or explicitly saying it was the
first sanctity. So how is רב נחמן Rav Nachman going to get
somebody to back him up? אלא, ella, says גמרא, Gemara, הני תנאי.
hanei Tannai. The following תנאים, Tannaim, דתניא, d'tanya, that
רב נחמן Rav Nachman is going to say, 'I'm going to find
somebody who agrees with me.' אמר רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי: amar Rabbi
Yishmael b'Rabbi Yose: למה מנו חכמים את אלו? lama manu chakhamim es
elu? So there's a list of these cities that are מוקפות חומה
mukafos chomah that are surrounded by a wall and therefore have certain
הלכות halakhos that apply to them, not just the ones that you
know which is reading of the מגילה, Megillah, but certain הלכות halakhos
about sending out, you know,
like the מצורעים, metzora'im, people that have צרעת, tzara'as, certain הלכות halakhos
about בתי ערי חומה, batei arei chomah, when you sell a house
in a city with a wall that after a year it gets,
you know, you can't redeem it. So there are all these
הלכות. halakhos. apply and the משנה mishna lists the cities that have
a wall. So the question is why is it listing it? Okay,
meaning why is it listing only these is the question. So let's
take a look. למה מנו חכמים את אלו, Lama manu chakhamim et
elu,
why were these listed? שכשעלו בני הגולה, shekeshealu benei hagola, מצאו אלו
וקדשום, matzu elu vekideshum,
because these were the ones that were resanctified in the time of
when they came up. Okay, so by the way, it's an interesting
phrase of sanctified. ירושלים Yerushalayim has a sanctity of like like you
know an extension of the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, but there is
some concept of all walled cities being able to be have a
sanctity of like מחנה ישראל, makhane Yisrael, you know and somehow have
a certain type of a sanctity for these הלכות halakhot of walled
cities. So he says that was sanctified in the time when they
came up. אבל ראשונות, Aval rishonot, but the for cities that had
been so it was only this list, meaning the question is why
only these? Aren't there a lot more walled cities? And the answer
is yeah, there are a lot more walled cities, but they didn't
make it for the second sanctity. They were not resettled when they
came up in the time of עזרא, Ezra, and that's why this
list is so short, okay? Because these were the ones that they
found and resanctified.
אבל ראשונות, Aval rishonot, but the first ones, the fuller list of
walled cities, בטלו משבטלה הארץ, batlu mishebatla haaretz, wasn't their status was
nullified when the when you know they went into exile. So this
finally רב נחמן's Rav Nakhman got a position that sides with him.
You know, now this isn't about the קדושה kedusha of the בית
המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, it's about a status of walled cities, but anyway
at least it's saying that there was a resanctification
at the time of עזרא Ezra and the sanctity from the first
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash did not last. So that finally is a
support to רב נחמן. Rav Nakhman. Okay, אלמא קסבר קדושה ראשונה קידשה
לשעתה ולא קידשה לעתיד לבוא. Alma kasavar kedusha rishona kidesha lishata velo
kidesha leatid lavo.
So you see it was only for that time and not for
future time. Okay, so that is a pretty good support, and that's
why what's considered a city of בתי ערי חומה, battei arei khoma,
right, is a smaller list than the than the list that was
at the time of יהושע בן נון, Yehoshua bin Nun, because it's
only the stuff from the time of the second בית המקדש, Beit
HaMikdash, so that shows it needed to be resanctified, and they had
the tools and the wherewithal to resanctify it. You didn't need all
the components. Okay, where
were we? Okay, רמיני, Remini, but one minute, I'll ask you, that
was a statement by רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי, Rabbi Yishmael berabbi Yosi,
here you have another statement of רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי Rabbi Yishmael
berabbi Yosi that says the opposite. אמר רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי, Amar
Rabbi Yishmael berabbi Yosi, וכי אלו בלבד היו? vekhi elu bilvad hayu?
Were these this list, is this the full list? Are these the
only cities that are surrounded by a wall? והלא כבר נאמר ששים
עיר כל
חבל ארגוב ממלכת עוג בבשן כל אלה ערים בצורות חומה גבוהה דלתים
ובריח, Vehala kevar neemar shishim ir kol khevel Argov mamlekhet Og babashan
kol ele arim betzurot khoma gevoha daltayim uvariakh, sixty cities! Sixty cities!
Just in עבר הירדן Ever HaYarden there were sixty cities that were
surrounded by walls. Why is this list so short? Okay, so now
we already heard one answer, but now we're going to hear a
different answer. אלא למה מנו חכמים את אלו, Ela lama manu khakhamim
et elu, so why was it only these that are on the
list? שכשעלו בני הגולה, shekeshealu benei hagola, because when they came up
from the exile, מצאו אלו וקדשום, matzu elu vekideshum, they found these
and they sanctified them. So now, the גמרא Gemara interrupts the interrupts
this quote, because because of what's going to come at the end,
because at the end we're going to say they didn't really resanctify
them. So the גמרא Gemara says, קדשום? Kideshum? קדשום השתא? Kideshum hashta?
What do you mean they sanctified them? הא מנא לקמן, Ha mina
lekaman, you're about to say in a minute, like you know, don't
like you know, I hate this when I'm trying to say something
and somebody interrupts me in the middle of a sentence when I'm
about to clarify what I'm about to say. So the גמרא Gemara
knows the end of the sentence and therefore it's interrupting now. You're
about to say at the end of your sentence, okay, דלא צריכי
לקדושי, delo tzrikhi lekidushi, that they don't need they didn't need to
be resanctified. The sanctity was from the first time of the בית
המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So what do you mean when they when they
came up they sanctified them? אלא מצאו אלו ומנאום. Ela matzu elu
umaneum. Okay, so now we're back to the משנה mishna after we've
edited it, or the ברייתא. braita. Okay, it's because when they came
up from the time of exile, they saw they found these cities,
maybe these cities still had walls, these were the cities they settled
in, and they listed them. These were the cities that they listed.
אבל, Aval, don't think that this list is complete. This is an
abbreviated list. Okay, that's what he's saying, different than the earlier earlier
quote. ולא אלו בלבד, Velo elu bilvad, it is not a full
list. This is just the ones that happened to be written down,
that happened to be counted when they came up at the exile.
אלא כל שתעלה לך מסורת מאבותיך שמוקפת
חומה מימות יהושע בן נון, Ela kol shetaale lekha mesoret meavotekha shemukeppet
khoma mimot Yehoshua bin Nun, anything that you have a tradition that
was surrounded by wall from the time of יהושע בן נון, Yehoshua
bin Nun, a phrase you know when it comes to מגילה Megilla
reading, כל מצות אלו נוהגות בה, kol mitzvot elu nohagot ba,
all of these מצות mitzvot about בתי ערי חומה battei arei khoma
etc. apply to it, okay? מפני שקדושה ראשונה קידשה לשעתה וקידשה לעתיד
לבוא, Mipnei shekedusha rishona kidesha lishata vekidesha leatid lavo,
because the first sanctity is still in force. So that's why it
said they didn't sanctify it when they came up, they just listed
them and counted them. So we have competing statements of רבי ישמעאל
ברבי יוסי, Rabbi Yishmael berabbi Yosi, right? You got a short list
of the בתי ערי חומה. battei arei khoma. One version of his
statement says these are the only ones that are sanctified, they needed
to resanctify and these were the and they only resanctified a small
subset when they came up in the time of the second בית
המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. And the first one says no, they're all holy
from the time of the first base I mean when they came
up in the time of the second בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. And
the other version of And says no, this is an abbreviated list.
Everything that was sanctified in the time of the first בית המקדש
Bais HaMikdash is still sanctified now. This list is just an abbreviated
list. So now the גמרא Gemara says we got a contradiction because
they're both in the same name of the same person. So the
גמרא Gemara says, קשיא דרבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי אדרבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי.
kashya d'Rabbi Yishmael bar Rabbi Yose ad'Rabbi Yishmael bar Rabbi Yose. He's
contradicting himself. אי בעית אימא תרי תנאי אליבא דרבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי.
ei bayis eima trei tannai aliba d'Rabbi Yishmael bar Rabbi Yose. Either
it's two תנאים tannaim who have different versions of what רבי ישמעאל
ברבי יוסי Rabbi Yishmael bar Rabbi Yose said. ואי בעית אימא, v'ei
bayis eima, and if you want I can tell you, חד מנייהו
רבי אלעזר ברבי יוסי אמרה, chad mineihu Rabbi Elazar bar Rabbi Yose
amrah, that one of them was a misquote. It wasn't רבי ישמעאל
ברבי יוסי, Rabbi Yishmael bar Rabbi Yose, it was רבי אלעזר ברבי
יוסי, Rabbi Elazar bar Rabbi Yose, because we know another line of
רבי אלעזר ברבי יוסי Rabbi Elazar bar Rabbi Yose that fits into
the idea that you go from the first בית המקדש Bais HaMikdash
based on if it was a walled city. דתניא, d'tanya, we learned
in a ברייתא, baraisa, רבי אלעזר ברבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Elazar bar
Rabbi Yose omer, אשר לא חומה, asher lo choma, something that has
a wall, but the word 'that has a wall', לא, lo, is
spelled with an אלף, aleph, which means 'doesn't have a wall'. It
should be spelled with a וו, vov, which means 'has a wall'.
So what's the story, does it or doesn't it? So his דרשה
drasha is אף על פי שאין לו עכשיו והיה לו קודם לכן.
af al pi she'ein lo achshav v'hayah lo kodem lachen. If it
had a wall in the past even though now it's לא חומה
lo choma with an אלף, aleph, doesn't have a wall, it's still
sanctified. So רבי אלעזר ברבי יוסי Rabbi Elazar bar Rabbi Yose says
as long as it basically had a wall in the time of
יהושע בן נון, Yehoshua bin Nun, it's still sanctified even though it
no longer has a wall. That's an idea that's consistent with the
idea of קדושה kedusha of the original קדושה kedusha still remains.
You have almost all of the תנאים tannaim are of the opinion
that it goes by at least the קדושה kedusha of the בית
המקדש, Bais HaMikdash, and now we've also thrown in ירושלים Yerushalayim and
בתי ערי חומה, Batei Arei Choma, again, not the land for agricultural
purposes, all seems to be from the first בית המקדש. Bais HaMikdash.
And what they did at עזרא Ezra they would say is only
a ritual, it's not הלכתית halachically significant. It's only some type of
a
זכר, zecher, a way of evoking the past, it's symbolically significant but
not הלכתית. halachically. And the other approach says no, the first sanctity
felt went away, they needed to resanctify it, and really you don't
need all those components, even one of those components is fine, and
therefore they really did resanctify it in the time of
עזרא. Ezra. Let's turn the page now. That was a lot of
fun. דף ט"ז עמוד ב'. daf tes zayin amud bais. New topic,
it's all related.
We've done with how you sanctify the space and did you need
to sanctify it, and now we're back to the idea that you
bring a קרבן korban when you enter in and you are טמא.
tamei. So the משנה mishna says if somebody became טמא tamei out
and entered in and they forgot the מקדש, mikdash, they forgot the
טומאה, tumah, they bring a קרבן. korban. But let's say somebody is
standing here in the עזרה Azara and
somehow some rodent runs up and dies on them and they touched
it and they became טמא tamei there. Are they חייב chayav a
קרבן? korban? Because they didn't enter into the בית המקדש Bais HaMikdash
בטומאה, b'tumah, they became טמא tamei there. So the משנה mishna says
that if you stay there long enough to do a prostration, or
if you actually prostrate yourself, or השתחויה, hishtachavaya, or if you leave
in a long way, a circuitous route rather than a short route,
all those ways basically if you stay too long, you are considered
to have entered in בטומאה b'tumah even though you didn't actually enter,
you just stayed, and that you would bring a קרבן. korban. Let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara wants to
know where do you know that staying is included in the prohibition
and in the bringing of a
קרבן. korban. נטמא בעזרה, nitma b'Azara, you became טמא tamei in the
עזרה, Azara, ונעלמה ממנו טומאה v'ne'elma mimenu tumah and then you forgot,
and then you realize, the whole shebang, but it was through staying
there not through entering there. So the גמרא Gemara says טומאה בעזרה
מנלן? tumah b'Azara minalan? Where do you know this from? Now the
question is possibly where do you know it's forbidden to stay there?
Or תוספות Tosafos says no, maybe it's obvious that it's forbidden to
stay there, but how do you know that you get כרת kares
for staying there? Because a קרבן korban is linked to the idea
of getting כרת, kares, almost all the times, there's a few exceptions,
but anyway טומאה tumah is not an exception, you only bring a
קרבן korban if you did a sin that's deserving of
כרת kares בשוגג, b'shogeg, unintentionally. So תוספות Tosafos says the verse that
says לא יטמאו את מחניהם, lo yetamu es machaneihem, do not impure,
purify, we understand that just staying in the בית המקדש Bais HaMikdash
would be a violation. But תוספות Tosafos more wants to know, says
that the גמרא's Gemara's question more is how do you know that
you get
כרת kares by staying
there? Because by כרת kares it more often says אל מקדש לא
יבאו, el mikdash lo yavo'u, do not enter into the מקדש. mikdash.
So either the question is how do you know it's forbidden and/or
how do you know you get כרת kares by staying there. אמר
רבי אלעזר, amar Rabbi Elazar, כתוב אחד אומר, kasuv echad omer, את
משכן ה' טמא, es mishkan Hashem timai, and the end of that
פסוק pasuk is
ונכרתה, v'nichrasa, because he impurified God's tent. וכתוב אחד אומר, v'kasuv echad
omer, the other one says כי את מקדש ה' טמא ונכרתה, ki
es mikdash Hashem timai v'nichrasa, because he impurified and he gets כרת.
kares. So both of those are פסוקים psukim about כרת. kares. אם
אינו ענין לטומאה שבחוץ, im eino inyan l'tumah shebachutz, now one of
them is extra, it's a little
redundant, if you don't need it for the scenario of getting טמא
tamei outside and entering in because you already accomplished that through one
פסוק, pasuk, תנהו ענין לטומאה שבפנים, tneihu inyan l'tumah shebifnim, so therefore
what the second פסוק pasuk tells you is even if you become
טמא tamei on the inside. בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Okay, now the
גמרא Gemara says, קראי מי יתרי? kra'ei mi yatrei? But one minute,
what makes you think the פסוקים psukim are extra? המידי צריכי, ha'midi
tzerichi, you need both פסוקים. psukim. You need both משכן Mishkan and
מקדש. Mikdash. Why? דתניא, Detanya, רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, נאמר
משכן למה נאמר מקדש, ne'emar Mishkan lamah ne'emar Mikdash, ונאמר מקדש למה
נאמר משכן? v'ne'emar Mikdash lamah ne'emar Mishkan? Why does it have to
say both? אילו נאמר משכן ולא נאמר מקדש, Ilu ne'emar Mishkan v'lo
ne'emar Mikdash, had it only said one, משכן, Mishkan, הייתי אומר, haisi
omer, על משכן יהא חייב, al Mishkan yehei chayav, שהרי משוח בשמן
המשחה. sheharei mashuach b'shemen hamishchah. Maybe you're only transgressor or get כרת,
karet, like this weighty punishment, when you enter into the משכן Mishkan
for the משכן Mishkan was sanctified with the, you know, anointing oil
and it was, you know, maybe it had a higher level of
sanctity to some degree. ועל מקדש לא יהא חייב, V'al Mikdash lo
yehei chayav, and maybe but you wouldn't get כרת karet for going
into the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash בטומאה. betumah. Maybe it doesn't have
the same sanctity. ואילו נאמר מקדש ולא נאמר משכן, V'ilu ne'emar Mikdash
v'lo ne'emar Mishkan, but the reverse is also true. Had it just
said you get כרת karet for going into the בית המקדש, Beis
Hamikdash, הייתי אומר, haisi omer, על מקדש יהא חייב, al Mikdash yehei
chayav, שהרי קדושתו קדושת עולם. sheharei kedushaso kedushas olam. That's for forever,
that sanctity. I'm going to go back and say something about that
word in a minute. ועל משכן לא יהא חייב, V'al Mishkan lo
yehei chayav, but the משכן Mishkan which is only temporary, maybe the
violation of that would not be deserving of כרת. karet. So you
could not infer one from the other. ולכך נאמר משכן ולכך נאמר
מקדש. V'lechach ne'emar Mishkan v'lechach ne'emar Mikdash. That's why it said both.
Okay, so therefore the גמרא Gemara says, you don't have an extra
פסוק. pasuk. You need it to say both משכן Mishkan and מקדש.
Mikdash. So how can you say something is extra here to teach
you even if you stay and you don't and it's not an
act of entering? So the גמרא Gemara says, רבי אליעזר הכי קא
קשיא ליה. Rabbi Eliezer hachi ka kashya lei. This is what was
bothering רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. מכדי, Michdi, let's take a look. משכן
אקרי מקדש ומקדש אקרי משכן. Mishkan ikri Mikdash u'Mikdash ikri Mishkan. You
really don't need to say both because one is called the other.
Okay, how do you know that?
נכתוב או אידי ואידי מקדש או אידי ואידי משכן. Nichtov o idi
v'idi Mikdash o idi v'idi Mishkan. You know, you could have said,
I'm sorry, רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, excuse me, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
who is saying, I misstated that a second ago, רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer who is stating that why did it have to say משכן
Mishkan and why did it have to say מקדש? Mikdash? Meaning there's
two things that are going on in the פסוקים psukim here. One
is that the פסוק pasuk is repeating itself. One says, משכן השם
טמא ונכרתה, Mishkan Hashem t'mei v'nichrasah, and the other says, מקדש השם
טמא ונכרתה. Mikdash Hashem t'mei v'nichrasah. So one question is, why do
you have to tell me twice you get כרת karet for being
טמא? tamei? That's one question, okay? And the answer to that is
the second time it's telling you that is to tell you even
if you just stay in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. The other
question is, fine, I get why you have to tell me twice,
but why did one of them say משכן Mishkan and one of
them say מקדש? Mikdash? And that's to tell me you can't infer
מקדש Mikdash from משכן, Mishkan, you have to actually say both explicitly.
So the גמרא Gemara is saying is both דרשות drashos are possible.
The redundancy that you get כרת karet when you enter in is
teaching you even if you stay in. And the switch of the
words from מקדש Mikdash to משכן Mishkan and saying one מקדש Mikdash
and one משכן Mishkan is to tell you that you could not
infer one from the other and that is you have to explicitly
tell me one is by מקדש Mikdash and one is by משכן.
Mishkan. רבי אליעזר הכי קא קשיא ליה. Rabbi Eliezer hachi ka kashya
lei. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer was not bothered by
הכי קא קשיא ליה. hachi ka kashya lei. מכדי משכן אקרי מקדש
ומקדש אקרי משכן. Michdi Mishkan ikri Mikdash u'Mikdash ikri Mishkan. נכתוב או
אידי ואידי. Nichtov o idi v'idi. So רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar who
said that, what do you call it, that, you know, it was
saying why once it says מקדש Mikdash and once it says משכן,
Mishkan, he wasn't dealing with the general redundancy of the verse. He
was dealing with the switch of terminology. The general redundancy is to
tell me even if you stay in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
He was focusing on why the switch in
terminology, okay? נכתוב או אידי ואידי מקדש או אידי ואידי משכן. Nichtov
o idi v'idi Mikdash o idi v'idi Mishkan. משכן ומקדש למה לי?
Mishkan u'Mikdash lamah li? Why did it switch terminology? שמע מינה תרתי,
Shma minah tarti, to tell you both things. To tell you A,
the redundancy tells you even if you stay you get כרת. karet.
Even if you don't enter בטומאה, betumah, you just stay בטומאה, betumah,
you get כרת. karet. And B, to tell me it applies both
to the מקדש Mikdash and the משכן. Mishkan. So now the גמרא
Gemara just finishes this up. בשלמא מקדש אקרי משכן, Bishlama Mikdash ikri
Mishkan, I get that the מקדש Mikdash is called a משכן. Mishkan.
דכתיב ונתתי משכני בתוככם. Dechisiv v'nasasi Mishkani b'sochachem. I will give my
משכני Mishkani in your midst. And this is in the פסוקים psukim
about, you
know, the ברכות, brachos, which is referring to what it's going to
be when they enter into the land of Israel. So even though
it says dwelling place, since it's a prophecy about what's going to
be when they enter the land of Israel, it's referring
to the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. אלא משכן דאקרי מקדש מנלן? Ella
Mishkan d'ikri Mikdash minalan? But where is the משכן Mishkan from the
time of the wilderness referred to as a מקדש? Mikdash? אילימא מדכתיב,
Ileima midechisiv, if you say
because it's written, ונסעו הקהתים נשאי המקדש, v'nas'u haKehosim nosei hamikdash, the
Kehosites who carry the מקדש Mikdash will travel forward. And that מקדש
Mikdash here you want to say refers to the whole building? No,
ההוא בארון כתיב. hahu b'aron kesiv. That doesn't mean the מקדש, Mikdash,
we're not referring to the whole building as the מקדש, Mikdash, the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. The מקדש Mikdash means the sanctified object, it
means the ארון. aron. But that's not referring to the whole משכן
Mishkan as the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. אלא מהכא, Ella mehacha, ועשו
לי מקדש ושכנתי בתוכם. v'asu li Mikdash v'shachanti b'socham. The command to
build the משכן Mishkan that's a pretty good proof ends with you
shall build for me a
sanctuary. So the משכן Mishkan is explicitly referred to as a מקדש.
Mikdash. You do by the way understand, meaning they obviously have different
connotations, right? משכן Mishkan means the sense of God's dwelling like שכינה;
Shechinah; מקדש Mikdash means the place becomes sanctified, okay? But מקדש Mikdash
also you understand why they're basically used in separate ways, I mean
both are true, right? But you know God's presence, you know God
dwelled, you know in whatever that means, you know when in the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and the משכן Mishkan was sanctified. But again,
because the משכן Mishkan was more portable, right? The sort of sense
of dwelling as opposed to like a permanent physical geographical space of
a domicile, right, which is more I think the sense you get
by the sense of like you know
מקדש. Mikdash. מקדש Mikdash is like a sanctifying of a concrete space,
you know, the space is sanctified, right? Whereas the משכן, Mishkan, you
know, God could dwell in different places and the משכן Mishkan sort
of moved. But they're both true and therefore the use of, they
can be used interchangeably, but the use of both is to tell
me that both are sanctified, that both have the same rule that
if you enter in טומאה, Tumah, you get כרת. Kares. Now there's
a fascinating long תוספות Tosafot here,
איבעי מקדש, Iba'i Mikdash, that תוספות Tosafot wants to know how come
sometimes the גמרא Gemara has to learn out that certain הלכות Halachot
apply equally to the מקדש Mikdash and the משכן Mishkan and how
come other times the גמרא Gemara doesn't need to learn it out
and takes it for granted that you can apply one to the
other? And תוספות's Tosafot best answer to this is that when the
issue has to do with something about the sanctity of the space,
then you need to say them separately. Okay, when it has to
do more with something like I don't know the function of קרבנות,
Korbanot, for example you can't bring קרבנות Korbanot until the gates of
the מקדש Mikdash are open, okay, there were the gates of the
היכל, Heichal, whatever, or the עזרה, Azarah, whatever, are open, he says
that's something that if it applies to one it applies to the
other. That's like the functions, you know, of the space, the functions
of the מקדש Mikdash and the משכן, Mishkan, you know. But when
it's dealing with the issue about the sanctity, there you might really
think that there's a different degree of sanctity. And if you think
about it, that gets to the issue I was talking about before,
right? The physical structure of the משכן Mishkan was more directly sanctified;
משה Moshe anointed it with the שמן המשחה, Shemen Hamishcha, there was
a direct sanctification of the actual beams of the physical structure, whereas
the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, like the ground was more sanctified and
that's the גמרא Gemara of קדושת עולם, Kedushat Olam, right? So when
it comes to the sanctity of the space, תוספות Tosafot says there
you need to sort of say it applies equally to both. What
does קדושת עולם Kedushat Olam mean by the way? So רש"י Rashi
says once the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash was built, you can never
you know take a look at רש"י, Rashi, right, he says קדושת
עולם, Kedushat Olam, three lines from the top, שאין אחריה היתר במות,
she'ein achareiha heter bamot, afterwards you could not bring something on a
במה, bamah, on a private altar, okay? תוספות Tosafot actually interestingly disagrees;
תוספות Tosafot thinks that maybe between the first and second בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash you were able to bring stuff on an altar, on
a private altar, which is pretty bizarre, but תוספות Tosafot says regardless
its קדושת עולם Kedushat Olam because it means if you ever want
another central מקדש, Mikdash, there's only one place from now on to
build it, which is you know הר הבית. Har Habayit. Especially by
the way if you say קדושה ראשונה קידשה לשעתה וקידשה לעתיד לבוא,
Kedusha rishona kidsha l'sha'ata v'kidsha l'atid lavo, which is just what we
got through learning, right? So then it really is קדושת עולם, Kedushat
Olam, right, it doesn't even need to be resanctified.
Okay, so now we continue. השתחוה
או ששהה כדי השתחויה. Hishtachavah o sheshaha k'dei hishtachavaya. Now, you transgress
if you wait the amount of time, if you actually do a
bowing down or you wait that amount of time. So אמר רבא,
Amar Rava, so the question's why do you have to say both,
right? Because once you say you wait that amount of time, it
covers also doing a bowing down, right? You get my point here?
If you say the amount of time it takes to bow down,
then you don't have to say or you bow down, right? Because
that took the amount of time, unless you could bow down in
quicker than the standard amount of time, which is what the גמרא
Gemara is going to say, okay. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, לא שנו
אלא שהשתחוה כלפי פנים. Lo shanu ella shehishtachavah klapei pnim. When is
it true that a bowing down you're חייב chayav even if, now
the presumption is even if it takes less than the standard amount
of time? When you bow down facing towards the, you know, facing
west, like it's considered an official השתחויה hishtachavah because it's facing God's
presence, alright? אבל השתחוה כלפי חוץ, Aval hishtachavah klapei chutz, but if
you do a bow down facing in the other direction, שאינו אלא
שהה, she'eino ella shaha, then you need the official amount of time.
איכא דמתני לה אסיפא, Ika d'matni lah asseifa, some give רבא's Rava
statement on the end of
the משנה: Mishnah: או ששהה כדי השתחויה. O sheshaha k'dei hishtachavaya. מכלל
דהשתחויה גופה בעי שהייה. Michlal d'hishtachavah gufah ba'i shehiyah. So one minute,
if you need to wait that amount of time, then it sounds
like that bowing down requires that amount of time, like that amount
of time should just be what dictates. Why do you have to
say and bow down? So אמר רבא, Amar Rava, לא, לא שנו
אלא שהשתחוה כלפי חוץ. Lo, lo shanu ella shehishtachavah klapei chutz. When
do you need to wait that amount of time? That's when you're
bowing down, you know, in an opposite direction, that's when a bowing
down would require that amount of time. אבל כלפי פנים, Aval klapei
pnim, but if you're bowing down in the right direction, then it's
just the act of bowing down. אף על גב דלא שהה. Af
al gav d'lo shaha. והכי קאמר, V'hachi ka'amar, here's how to read.
the משנה: Mishnah: השתחויה כלפי פנים, hishtachvaya klapei pnim, if you bow
down in an official one, which is towards the inside, או ששהה
כדי שחויה, o she-shaha kedei shachvaya, בהכי שחויה דכלפי חוץ חייב, be-hachi
shachvaya de-klapei chutz chayav, or if you bowed down in a if
you waited that amount of time for a bowing down towards the
outside, you'd be חייב. chayav. Okay, it seems a little complicated here's
the way of reading the משנה, Mishnah, but the basic point is,
the משנה Mishnah mentions either bowing down or waiting the amount of
time. And what רבא Rava is saying is, so that means that
your bowing down that you're חייב chayav for is a faster bowing
down than the normal amount of time, but that would only be
when it is an official bowing down, a השתחויה hishtachvaya that we
recognize as meaningful, which is השתחויה hishtachvaya towards the inside. When you
do that type of השתחויה, hishtachvaya, even if you do it fast,
you still are חייב. chayav.
Okay, this is just to stop us from bowing down in the
opposite direction?
Yes, but we're not getting into that. That's not relevant. It just
means that then it is disrespectful, but it also but it also
that means that's why we're not recognizing it as a השתחויה. hishtachvaya.
So ironically, even though you did something more disrespectful, if you did
a fast and got out of the בית המקדש Beis Ha-Mikdash fast,
you wouldn't be חייב chayav because you didn't wait the amount of
time and you didn't do something that was recognized as a השתחויה.
hishtachvaya. Okay.
Why does somebody bow down in the opposite direction?
They don't know better, I don't know. I mean, it doesn't have
to be intentional disrespect. Okay. Okay. היכי
דמי? heichi dami? Now the גמרא Gemara says, היכי דמי השתחויה דאית
בה שהייה והיכי דמי השתחויה דלית בה שהייה? heichi dami hishtachvaya d'is
bah shehiya v'heichi dami hishtachvaya d'leis bah shehiya? So I don't understand,
meaning I was just sort of saying maybe the guy's really fast,
but the גמרא Gemara doesn't sort of imagine that, it imagines that
there must be two types of bowing down, like one that is
the long one that takes more time, and that's the one that
when we mean when we say the full amount of time, and
one that's a shorter bowing down, and that's the one that you
could be חייב chayav for even if you didn't wait the amount
of time. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: דלית בה שהייה
זו כריעה בעלמא. d'leis bah shehiya zo kriah be-alma. With
the shorter one is that is when you just get down on
your knees, כריעה בעלמא kriah be-alma היא. hi. דאית בה שהייה, d'is
bah shehiya,
the one that takes
that's the measurement of the time, that's the longer one, פישוט ידים
ורגלים pishut yadayim v'raglayim is fully spreading out your arms. You're down
on your knees and you're going down with your arms. So the
basic הלכה halacha is like this: the amount of time is if
you just go down on your knees and that's it. I mean,
that's like a type of a bowing and then you get up
and then you leave, you did a if you did it towards
the inside, you did a השתחויה hishtachvaya
and therefore it doesn't matter how long it took you, even though
that was only it only took you two seconds. Okay, but if
you wait the amount of time it takes you to do this
and to do this and then to get up, which is maybe
what, three seconds, four seconds, then even if you didn't bow down.
So we measure the amount of time by doing a full השתחויה,
hishtachvaya, that's maybe let's call it four seconds. So if you wait
four seconds you're חייב, chayav, I don't know, maybe it's longer, maybe
it's to pray also while you're down, I don't know. Okay, but
if you do a short השתחויה hishtachvaya just on your knees and
you do it in the right
direction, then you're חייב chayav even if it didn't take you that
amount of time, even if it didn't take you the full four
seconds. Okay. So let's take a look. וכמה שיעור שהייה? v'kama shiur
shehiya? Now how long is that? The amount of time of waiting
to do a full השתחויה? hishtachvaya? So פליגי בה רב יצחק בר
נחמני וחד דעמיה. paligi bah Rav Yitzchak bar Nachmani v'chad d'imei. So
this was a debate of רב יצחק בר נחמני Rav Yitzchak bar
Nachmani and his colleague. ומאן ניהו? u-man nihu? Who was his colleague?
רבי שמעון בן פזי. Rabbi Shimon ben Pazi. Okay, so that's one
way of telling who the debate was between. ואמרי לה, v'amrei lah,
and some have the version the other way: רבי שמעון בן פזי
וחד דעמיה, Rabbi Shimon ben Pazi v'chad d'imei, the debate was between
רבי שמעון בן פזי Rabbi Shimon ben Pazi and his colleague starting
in the other direction. ומאן ניהו? u-man nihu? And who's that? רב
יצחק בר נחמני. Rav Yitzchak bar Nachmani. So at that stage we're
saying it's all the same two people just how you say it.
But here's a different version: ואמרי לה רבי שמעון בר נחמני. v'amrei
lah Rabbi Shimon bar Nachmani. It wasn't רב יצחק בר נחמני, Rav
Yitzchak bar Nachmani, it was רבי שמעון בר נחמני. Rabbi Shimon bar
Nachmani. Anyway, these two debated. חד אמר כמימרא דהאי פסוקא. chad amar
k'memra d'hai pasuka. One says the amount of time is as long
as it takes you to say the following פסוק pasuk which we'll
quote in a
minute. וחד אמר כמבויחראו לסופא, v'chad amar k'mivayichru l'sofa, only the second
half of the פסוק pasuk starting from the word and they bowed
down. What's the פסוק? pasuk? Here's the פסוק: pasuk: וכל בני ישראל
v'chol b'nei Yisrael רואים ברדת האש, ro'im b'redes ha-esh, all בני ישראל
b'nei Yisrael saw the fire coming down, וכבוד ה' על הבית, u-chvod
Hashem al ha-bayis, and the honor of God was on the house,
ויכרעו, vayichru, that's the middle of the פסוק, pasuk, ויכרעו אפים ארצה
vayichru apayim artza with their face to the ground על הרצפה al
ha-ritzpah on the ground
וישתחוו והודות לה' כי טוב כי לעולם חסדו. v'yishtachavu v'hodos l'Hashem ki
tov ki l'olam chasdo. Okay, so how long would it take to
say that? Three seconds, four seconds, whatever it would be. It's not
a long amount of time. And one says the whole פסוק pasuk
and the other says only from the words they bowed down till
the end of the פסוק. pasuk. Okay, so we're not talking about
a lot of time, we're talking about like two, three, four seconds.
All right. So if you wait the amount of time of saying
that פסוק, pasuk, which is the amount of time it takes to
just do a full השתחויה, hishtachvaya, you're
חייב, chayav, but if you bow down, you're חייב chayav even if
you don't wait that amount of time, even if you just bow
down on your knees, assuming that you bow down in the right
direction. Let's just read one more line. תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. קידה,
kidah, when it says
ויקודו, v'yikdu, when they prostrated, על אפים. al apayim. That means actually
your face is against the ground. Okay. וכן הוא אומר, v'chein hu
omer, ותקוד בת שבע אפים ארץ. va-tikod Bas-sheva apayim aretz.
And בת שבע Bas-sheva prostrated herself with her face to the ground.
face to the ground. So the word קידה kida is a bowing
down as a prostrating with your face to the ground. כריעה, kriya,
when it says bowed, just the word bowed, על ברכיים, al birkayim,
that's just on the knees. וכן הוא אומר, v'chen hu omer, מכרוע
על ברכיו. mikroa al birkav. He arose from bowing down on his
knees. Crouching, I guess we would say. Okay. השתחוויה, hishtachavaya, again to
prostrate, to bow down, but זו פשוט ידיים ורגליים. zu pishut yadayim
v'raglayim. It's outstretching the arms, but not necessarily putting the face against
the ground, right? So you can see that, right? This is, right,
this is כריעה, kriya, this is השתחוויה, hishtachavaya, and
then that's קידה, kida,
right, when you go all the way. You just have to look
at a picture of like when they do, you know, Muslim prayer
like you see the stages, right?
Okay, what is it when it says and he
fell on his face like ויפל על פניו? vayippol al panav? Yeah,
and he fell on his face. Yeah, that's a good question. I
don't know if that means, I don't know if that is interpreted
to mean an act of prostrating like because it's usually ויפל על
פניו vayippol al panav is normally not, I mean we do say
נפילת אפים nefilat apayim like, yeah, it's a good question. That's the
phrase we use when we do תחנון, tachanun, right?
I don't know if it's often used in the same sense of
worship, like השתחוויה hishtachavaya is normally a way of showing honor. Like
you can bow down to a person and it's a way of
like, you know, you can bow down and give thanks to God.
ויפל על פניו vayippol al panav is usually a sense of maybe
submission or fear. It's an interesting question, I'd have to think more
about that. But it's not exactly the same act and the same
significance. Okay? Okay. וכן הוא אומר, v'chen hu omer, הבוא נבוא אני
ואמך ואחיך להשתחוות לך
ארצה. havo navo ani v'imcha v'achecha l'hishtachavot l'cha artza. Okay, so you
see that השתחוויה hishtachavaya is to the ground, but it doesn't mention
the face. Okay, תוספות Tosfos is bothered because sometimes face is mentioned
by השתחוויה hishtachavaya and whatever, but anyway those are basically the three
different degrees. Okay, we will end here.